So, the mainframe handles a whole lot of transactions.
And it's important that they be fast and accurate.
But it's also extremely important that the data for these transactions be safe and secure.
Safe to say, in today's information economy, a large-scale data breach is one of the
worst things that can happen.
So how do we make sure that the data in these transactions is kept safe from prying eyes?
One of the most commonly used practices is encryption.
Basically scrambling data in such a way we can control who is able to de-scramble it.
There are a number of encryption algorithms and practices we can use to handle the encryption
and decryption of data, but it all comes down to controlling who has the keys.
In cryptography, a key is just a series of characters.
How many characters generally depends on the strength of the encryption.
If my key is only three bits with each bit, either being a one or a zero, there's
only eight possible ways we can flip those bits.
So not much of a key at all.
Every time you add a bit, you double the amount of possible combinations someone would
have to guess.
So four bits gets you to 16, five bits gets you to 32, fast-forward to 64 bits, and you've
got billions of possible combinations.
But even that's guessable with enough time and dedicated resources.
So for very important data, you'll often see 256 bit and higher levels of encryption.
And those keys will get refreshed from time to time just to minimize the possibility
of them getting figured out and exploited.
One of the most basic forms of securing data is what's called symmetric encryption.
In this method, there's a key that both encrypts and decrypts data.
And you give a copy of that key to anyone who has a need to access the data.
It works, but it's difficult to scale up while keeping it secure, and you also have to
distribute those keys to all the intended users.
This is where public key cryptography comes in.
In public key cryptography, there are two keys, a public key and a private key.
And their mathematically linked in such a way that the public key can be used to encrypt
a message, and only the private key that's linked to that public key can decrypt it.
So I can give out my public key to pretty much anyone.
They can't use that to figure out my private key, and all it means is they can encrypt
a message in such a way that only I can decrypt it.
And if I want to send a message to my friend, and I want to make sure no one else can decrypt
it, I can encrypt it with their public key, so they can decrypt it with their private
key.
Pop quiz time.
You got that?
Good.
Now, public and private keys can be used for some other pretty interesting things, like
signing documents and creating hashes for data, which reveal if any of the data has been
tampered with.
Both of these are incredibly important functions of cryptography and used extensively
in business.
This whole idea of public and private key infrastructure only works if private keys are
kept private.
That is key.
Guys?
Key?
The IBMZ has dedicated facilities and hardware to enable, accelerate, and further secure
these cryptographic functions.
For starters, there's CPACF, the CP Assist for cryptographic functions.
This is a functionality provided on the processors specifically built largely around symmetric
key functions.
And can greatly speed up things like VPN, SSL, and data storing applications.
There's also the Crypto Express PCIe card.
This is a dedicated card that handles more advanced cryptographic functions.
By offloading cryptographic work to specialize software and hardware, we were able to keep
our keys safe while still making encryption, decryption, and other cryptographic capabilities
readily available to all aspects of Z data processing.
And I do mean all aspects, because starting with the Z14 version of the IBMZ mainframe,
there's a feature called pervasive encryption, which lets us more easily keep data encrypted
while still allowing us and others to manage that data.
That way, it only needs to be decrypted at the moment it's actually needed, minimizing
the possibility of confidential data being seen by people who shouldn't have access.
This feature gets a lot of its functionality from CPACF and Crypto Express.
There are some other important and interesting considerations when it comes to crypto
and practice.
In the next video, you'll hear a little bit more about that from my buddy, Mark.